<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startup on Francisco Santolo</title>
    <link>https://natos.github.io/franciscosantolo.com/tags/startup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startup on Francisco Santolo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://natos.github.io/franciscosantolo.com/tags/startup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Entrepreneurship success formula</title>
      <link>https://natos.github.io/franciscosantolo.com/post/entrepreneurship-success-formula/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natos.github.io/franciscosantolo.com/post/entrepreneurship-success-formula/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We reveal the Startup Success formula, which radically diverges from Startup Ecosystem Gurus&amp;rsquo; and Key Players&amp;rsquo; recommendations: VCs or Venture Capitals, Accelerators, Incubators, Speakers, Angel Investors, top-notch Universities around the world, and Governments (who follow the actual rules, usually with good intentions and lack of knowledge)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurship (as we now call the process of turning the founder&amp;rsquo;s vision into a &amp;laquo;sustainable&amp;raquo;, real venture) has taken a mixture of courage, intuition, emotional intelligence (resilience, antifragility), access to resources and networks for hundreds, thousands of years. Kind of an art. But to better understand our Formula there&amp;rsquo;s something you need to know. Starting around 7 years ago amazing authors have figured the way to build powerful step by step practical methodologies that can lead you to reduce your risks, map where you are standing and seriously maximize your chances of success. Have a look at some of the fundamental top-notch literature we follow at Scalabl Global, which is incorporated into our own proprietary Startup Methodology. In 2017, by training in our formula at our Scalabl Academy, we have built over 100 companies with: 0 investment (yes, 0 investment!), low risk, high profitability, and possible scalab(i)l(ity) companies with over 350 entrepreneurs that are now part of our Alumni Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startup Ecosystem Gurus and respected institutions mention and recommend these SAME Books but ACT and guide their Entrepreneurs in the opposite way! (lack of reading? economical interest? both?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let me explain it in a very simplified way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Financial intermediaries (VCs) raise money from high wealth investors (they are recommended to assign a part of their wealth to &amp;laquo;risky&amp;raquo; investments, &amp;laquo;put your eggs in different baskets&amp;raquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) They charge an annual administration fee of 2-6% for the money they raise which they should use to build a capable team with Startup knowledge to choose the highly scalable and profitable Startups (3% of 100M is 3M, 3% of 1B, is 30M)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) But why spending that money if you can keep it as profit? How? by instrumenting a low fixed cost structure, hiring analysts (with fancy titles) just out from MBA, and partnering with &amp;laquo;Accelerators&amp;raquo;, &amp;laquo;Incubators&amp;raquo;, &amp;laquo;Universities&amp;raquo;, and now &amp;laquo;TV Shows&amp;raquo; for them to organize &amp;laquo;Contests&amp;raquo;, &amp;laquo;Competitions&amp;raquo;, &amp;laquo;Business Plans&amp;raquo;, &amp;laquo;Elevator Pitches&amp;raquo;, where they can disburse it quickly and in little parts (50k? 150k?). Quickly is very convenient, it means telling investors their money is already allocated (very important in the financial world, cause you are looking for return, and time is money) and with a good criteria (&amp;laquo;they won a contest where thousands participated! Wow!&amp;raquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) A panel of distinguished C-Level executives, Millionares, Billionares or leaders from the same Startup Ecosystem are then invited as honorary &amp;laquo;judges&amp;raquo; to choose the winners in an elevator pitch competition. Let me ask you something:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you really give your money to people you don&amp;rsquo;t know for a risky investment by seeing them dress well, speak &amp;laquo;correctly&amp;raquo; for 5 minutes and briefly (not to bore the honorary Judges or disturbe &amp;laquo;important&amp;raquo; agendas) describe some kind of plan and answer a couple of bad &amp;laquo;TV show type&amp;raquo; questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am permanently invited as Judge and president of the Jury to many of this competitions, organized with the best of the intentions (I&amp;rsquo;m being serious here), by Governments, NGOs, or Universities, to help entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear them speak, they haven&amp;rsquo;t been trained, they don&amp;rsquo;t know the methodologies, they don&amp;rsquo;t have a clear business model, and worst of all: They are going to get the money!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone will profit from them getting that money! More funds will be raised! More administration fees will be charged! Everyone will profit but them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not by chance the Startup Ecosystem &amp;laquo;traditional knowledge&amp;raquo; measures success and Startup maturity as the number of rounds (series A, B, C etc), the amount of funds raised, or how many &amp;laquo;Exits&amp;raquo; an Entrepreneur has had!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Then, when the entrepreneur signs the contract (oh, if you read those contracts!) she/he immediately becomes a modern slave (or as I call it, labor without labor rights!). He becomes an actor, pitching full time, selling an image to the world, to their friends, to their families. He becomes a fake hero! And his anguish is strong. He internally knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no clear Business Model, results are not coming, they are trying to scale without a proven sales roadmap by pushing demand with more investment. More revenue brings more valuation and illusion of success. More illusion of success (and finishing of cash) makes more rounds, more pitches and more profits for everyone (unless cash is not raised and the entrepreneur is the last to cash out, he looses everything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if things go &amp;laquo;well&amp;raquo;, everyone will assure their exit before the entrepreneur does, or if it goes even better, they will assure the entrepreneur&amp;rsquo;s exit by firing the founder and keeping the company (after so many equity dilution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) What makes it worst: in a world of high liquidity (very low interest rates) almost everyone with access to a network of highly rich people can build a Venture Capital (VC), with the resulting low level of knowledge about Startups and the propensity and incentive to win money before the bubble bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, knowledge and methodology are clearly one part of the formula. Not following the Ecosystem advice and raising seed funds is another. What are we missing? We are getting there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you a short story. In 2015 I graduated from Stanford Innovation and Entrepreneurship Certificate, learning important tools and literature that were important departure points for my continuous learning. But in 2013, in a General Management Program in Kellogg School of Management Brian Uzzi had taught me a concept that would become very powerful and life changing: Networking! (Read later this 2015 article: Entrepreneurship through Networking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please hear 1 minute of the Graduation Speech at Stanford to introduce this important part of the formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MM8xh_K6Z2I --&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;embed video-player&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;youtube-player&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MM8xh_K6Z2I&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c8GWzyTDuQI&amp;amp;t&#34;&gt;(You can see the full Stanford Graduation speech later here)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networking, Community, Taking care of others, giving first are clearly what makes the magic happen (sounds counter intuitive? eh? But try it, it certainly works! and it makes you happy!). They are concepts we have mastered at Scalabl by building a talented, diverse and collaborative Alumni community, where we help each other succeed, we share our contacts and networks with trust, we sell for each other, we buy our products, we supply to each other, we think together, and free our times to give free advice or consultancy to the network from our experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when it comes to the Startup Success Formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurship continues to be some kind of art, but top-notch authors, methodology, and easiness of communication fueled by social networks, access to computational power, possibility of outsourcing almost anything to any part of the world, and exponential technologies allow for greater possibilities and guide than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if startup success can&amp;rsquo;t be reduced to a precise or statistical Formula (I believe it would be terribly boring if we could), take it as a simple way to explain our practical learnings (by utilizing our methodology with over 350 Alumni on more than 100 real companies) on which things to pursue (+) and which ones to avoid (-) for early stage startup success. In a sense, each component is like the ingredient of a recipe, and the trick is to mix them in the right way on a case by case basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early Stage Startup Success = Knowledge (methodology, reading, learning from others, formulating and testing hypothesis instead of executing tight plans) + Community (Networking, diversity, learning how to listen and ask open questions, giving always first, there&amp;rsquo;s something easy for you that is important for others, sharing purpose) + Hard Work (don&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s easy!) + Emotional Intelligence (the same resilience, antifragility, and attributes, kind of an art old entrepreneurs used to have) - #Risk (reduced fixed costs, asset light Business Models where you get paid before you produce or need to pay your suppliers) [This #Risk part will be explained in a future article and it is a fundamental part of our own methodology. For now see John Mullins&amp;rsquo; great book: &amp;laquo;The Customer Funded Business&amp;raquo;] - Seed Capital (which we are sure hurts entrepreneurs at this stage)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Scalabl we call ourselves a People Capital cause our community works to transform the world for good by developing one entrepreneur at a time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s our focus on people, values, continuous learning and practical application in the real world, over focusing on raising money just for raising that makes the real difference!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already in Argentina, Mexico, and in 2018 we are launching in UK, Hong Kong, United Arab Emirates, India, Portugal and Saudi Arabia [Yes, with 0 external investment or founders capital, just cash generation]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/startup-hacker-francisco-santolo/?lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_pulse_read%3B%2B1MdhRIOR9ace%2B6mvFbcLQ%3D%3D&#34;&gt;See what Forbes had to say about us only one year after our creation in 2017! The Startup Hacker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! If you are entrepreneur or an investor, at least take this different view as something to weight versus the totally agreeing Startup Ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before an idea is disruptive, it is totally crazy [Peter Diamandis]!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>